Guide to the Arlen Specter Senatorial Papers, Group 10. Electronic Records, 1980-2010 TJU.2010.01.10
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Arlen Specter Senatorial Papers, Group 10. Electronic Records
1980-2010
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Specter, Arlen
TJU.2010.01.10
61 folders 209 GB
The Arlen Specter Senatorial Papers, Group 10. Electronic Records contains born-digital and digitized material reflecting work done within Senator Specter's office. Specter served as U.S. Senator from 1981 to 2011, making him the longest-tenured Pennsylvanian senator. The contents of the drives include memos, photos, correspondence, constituent mail, reports, form letters, newsclips, and legislative information.
Custodial History
Material was transferred to the care of Philadelphia University in 2010-2011 from the Federal Records Storage Facility in Suitland, Maryland, as well as the Senator's Washington, D.C. and Pennsylvania offices. The physical material was transferred to the University of Pittsburgh in 2014, with the exception of selected photographic and memorabilia items that remain at the Arlen Specter Center's Roxboro House for display. In 2016, Philadelphia University merged with Thomas Jefferson University, and is now known as Thomas Jefferson University- East Falls campus.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Arlen Specter to Philadelphia University in 2010. Philadelphia University and the University of Pittsburgh entered into a partnership to jointly manage the collection in 2013.
Biography
Born in Wichita, Kansas, on February 12, 1930, Arlen Specter came to Pennsylvania to attend the University of Pennsylvania. He married Joan Levy in 1953, and graduated from Yale Law School in 1956. He became assistant district attorney in Philadelphia in 1959. In 1962, Specter was recommended to serve on the Warren Commission, assembled to investigate the assassination of President John F. Kennedy. As part of the Commission, he was responsible for co-authoring the proposal of the "single bullet theory," determining that one bullet struck both President Kennedy and Texas Governor John Connally. Specter ran for Philadelphia district attorney in 1965, switching his Party membership to Republican in order to unseat the incumbent Democrat. He was successful, and served as district attorney from 1966 to 1974.
After an initial failed run for Senator and then for Governor of Pennsylvania, Specter was elected to the U.S. Senate in 1980. He would stay in this position from 1981 to 2011, making him the longest-tenured senator in Pennsylvania's history. During this time, he was a member of a number of Committees: Judiciary (1981-2011; Chair, 2007-2007), Appropriations (1981-2011), Veterans Affairs (1981-2011; Chair, 1997-2001 and 2003-2005), Select Intelligence (1985-1991; 1995-1997; Chair, 1995-1997), Special Aging (1991-1995; 2007-2011), Governmental Affairs (1997-2001; 2003-2005), and Environment and Public Works (2001-2003; 2009-2011).
Though elected as a Republican, Specter was a moderate on many issues, including healthcare reform, immigration, and abortion. He would often cross party lines, such as in voting against the confirmation of President Ronald Reagan's nominee Judge Robert Bork to the Supreme Court in 1987. Specter would again come into the spotlight during a Supreme Court nomination process in 1991, for his cross-examination of Professor Anita Hill regarding her allegations against nominee Clarence Thomas. In 1999, he would vote against the charges brought against President Bill Clinton, giving an answer of "not proven" to reflect his belief that Clinton had not received a fair trial.
As Senator, Specter championed a number of causes and influenced many legislative areas. He was frequently a member of Congressional Delegation trips, particularly to the Middle East, where he would speak out on the cause of freedom from religious persecution and the importance of strong diplomatic relations. He was also a proponent of funding for medical research, including the use of stem cells. He advocated for strict crime laws, particularly for career criminals. His focus on benefitting Pennsylvania could be seen through the pursuit of grant funding opportunities and his attempt to prevent the closure of the Philadelphia Naval Shipyard in the 1990s.
With the worsening of Congressional partisanship in the late 2000s, Specter found himself frequently voting with his Democratic peers. After being one of only three handful of Republicans to vote for the American Recovery and Reinvestment Act in 2009, Specter found himself increasingly marginalized within his party. In April 2009, he returned to the Democratic Party, helping to ensure the passage of the Affordable Care Act. Seeking re-election in 2010, he was defeated in the Democratic primary by Joe Sestak.
Specter's 30-year tenure in the Senate concluded in January 2011. After leaving the Senate, he partnered with Philadelphia University (now Jefferson-East Falls) to establish the Arlen Specter Center for Public Service. In the fall of 2012, Specter, who had previously beaten Hodgkin's lymphoma in 2005 while serving as Chair of the Judiciary Committee, was diagnosed with cancer. He died on October 14, 2012, aged 82.
Access Restrictions
No restrictions.
These materials are accessible via the Digital Asset Machine in the University of Pittsburgh Archives Service Center Reading Room. Please contact Archive & Special Collections for additional information.
Scope and Content Notes
The Arlen Specter Senatorial Papers, Group 10. Electronic Records contains born-digital and digitized material reflecting work done within Senator Specter's office. The majority of the electronic records were found on two hard drives containing material from the Senator's Washington, D.C. and regional offices, though a small amount was found in the analog collection. Material on the hard drives was arranged to mimic the structure of the physical collection. The contents of the drives include memos, photos, correspondence, constituent mail, reports, form letters, newsclips, and legislative information.
Arrangement
Group 10 is arranged into two series:
Series I. Office Hard Drives, 1981-2010
Series II. Analog Collection, 1995-2006
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
All material in this group is accessible via the Digital Access Machine located in the Archives Service Center Reading Room.
Related Material
Arlen Specter Senatorial Papers, Group 1. Pre-Senatorial Career Files, 1953-1980, TJU.2010.01.01
Arlen Specter Senatorial Papers, Group 2. Legislative Files, 1965-2011, TJU.2010.01.02
Arlen Specter Senatorial Papers, Group 3. Personal, Political and Official Files, 1944-2010, TJU.2010.01.03
Arlen Specter Senatorial Papers, Group 4. Office Administration Files, 1962-2010, TJU.2010.01.04
Arlen Specter Senatorial Papers, Group 5. Constituent Services Files, 1976-2007, TJU.2010.01.05
Arlen Specter Senatorial Papers, Group 6. Public Relations and Media Files, 1972-2010, TJU.2010.01.06
Arlen Specter Senatorial Papers, Group 7. Campaign Files, 1976-2004, TJU.2010.01.07
Arlen Specter Senatorial Papers, Group 8. Awards and Memorabilia, 1957-2010, TJU.2010.01.08
Arlen Specter Senatorial Papers, Group 9. Photographs, 1930-2010, TJU.2010.01.09
Pennsylvania; Memorandums; Reports; Photographs; Politicians; United States. Congress. Senate; Specter, Arlen
- Office Hard Drives, 1980-2010; I.
  Scope and Content Notes
  Office Hard Drives contain the contents of two hard drives transferred to Philadelphia University from Senator Specter's Washington, D.C. and regional offices. Material on the hard drives was arranged to mimic the structure of the physical collection. The contents of the drives include memos, photos, correspondence, constituent mail, reports, form letters, newsclips, and legislative information.
  - Legislative Files, 1981-2010
    - Appropriations Committee, 2009-2010 (Folder 1)
    - Floor statements, 1981-2009 (Folder 2)
    - Legislative activity, 1981-2010 (Folder 3)
    - Legislative assistants, 1981-2010 (Folder 4)
    - Research files, 1995-2002 (Folder 5)
    - Specter career committee assignments, 2010 (Folder 6)
  - Personal Political Official Files, 1993-1999
    - VIP mail, 1993-1999 (Folder 7)
  - Office Administration Files, 1981-2010
    - Administrative assistants, 1981-2010 (Folder 8)
    - Memos, 1999-2010 (Folder 9)
    - Shared office files, 1981-2010 (Folder 10)
    - Specter career staff, 2010 (Folder 11)
  - Constituent Services Files, 1981-2005
    - Constituent correspondence, 1981-2005 (Folder 12)
    - County accomplishments, 1982-1998 (Folder 13)
    - Form responses, 1999-2005 (Folder 14)
  - Public Relations and Media Files, 1988-2010
    - Book interviews, 1998 (Folder 15)
    - Charles Robbins, 2008-2010 (Folder 16)
    - Newsletters, 2005-2006 (Folder 17)
    - Press clips, 1988-2007 (Folder 18)
    - Tapes inventory, 2010 (Folder 19)
  - Awards and Memorabilia, 1981-2010
    - Memorabilia, 1981-2010 (Folder 20)
  - Photographs, 1981-2010
    - 1981 (Folder 21)
    - 1982 (Folder 22)
    - 1983 (Folder 23)
    - 1984 (Folder 24)
    - 1985 (Folder 25)
    - 1986 (Folder 26)
    - 1987 (Folder 27)
    - 1988 (Folder 28)
    - 1989 (Folder 29)
    - 1990 (Folder 30)
    - 1991 (Folder 31)
    - 1992 (Folder 32)
    - 1993 (Folder 33)
    - 1994 (Folder 34)
    - 1995 (Folder 35)
    - 1996 (Folder 36)
    - 1997 (Folder 37)
    - 1998 (Folder 38)
    - 1999 (Folder 39)
    - 2000 (Folder 40)
    - 2001 (Folder 41)
    - 2002 (Folder 42)
    - 2003 (Folder 43)
    - 2004 (Folder 44)
    - 2005 (Folder 45)
    - 2006 (Folder 46)
    - 2007 (Folder 47)
    - 2008 (Folder 48)
    - 2009 (Folder 49)
    - 2010 (Folder 50)
    - Office photos, DC, 2010 (Folder 51)
    - Outside images, 2004-2010 and undated (Folder 52)
    - Portraits, 1983-1988 and undated (Folder 53)
- Analog Collection, 1995-2006; II.
  Analog Collection Files includes material taken from disks found in the Legislative Assistant Files series of the physical collection. They include reports and legislative material.
  - Chris Bradish, Defense, Anthrax, 2002 (Folder 1)
  - Chris Bradish, Defense, Appropriations, 2003 (Folder 2)
  - Chris Bradish, Defense, Appropriations requests, 2001-2003 (Folder 3)
  - Chris Bradish, Defense, NAVAIR, 2003 (Folder 4)
  - Chris Bradish, Defense, Sea Cadets, 2001 (Folder 5)
  - Chris Bradish, Foreign affairs, United Nations trip, 2006 (Folder 6)
  - Tom Dower, Agriculture and Nutrition, Farm Bill, 2001-2002 (Folder 7)
  - Richard Hertling, Regulatory Transition Act, 1995 (Folder 8)